<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The organs funerall or the quiristers lamentation for the abolishment of superstition and superstitious ceremonies. In a dialogicall discourse between a quirister and an organist, An. Dom. 1642.</title>
            <author>Brookbank, Joseph, b. 1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4975A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E141_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21845</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871521</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871521</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156555</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77626)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156555)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 25:E141[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The organs funerall or the quiristers lamentation for the abolishment of superstition and superstitious ceremonies. In a dialogicall discourse between a quirister and an organist, An. Dom. 1642.</title>
                  <author>Brookbank, Joseph, b. 1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for George Kirby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1642?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Religion --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156555:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156555:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ORGANS FVNERALL OR THE QUIRISTERS LAMENTATION FOR THE ABOLISHMENT Of Superſtition and Superſtitious Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>In a Dialogicall Diſcourſe between a Quiriſter and an Organiſt, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> printed for <hi>George Kirby.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:156555:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156555:2"/>
            <head>The Qreriſters Lamentation for the Aboliſhment of Superſtition and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſtitious Ceremonies.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Queriſter.</speaker>
               <p>WOe and alas, the day of abſolution is at hand whereby wee ſhall be freed from our ſinnes of ſuperſtition a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God in his Service with ſuperfluous Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, which now is termed by many Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous rags of Popery, the originall whereof they ſay came from the Pope, which is called Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and introduced into our Church by the great Patriarch at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> which if a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had not hapned in the Climactericall yeare of his fall, and that he had but obtained the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of a Cardinall, we might then have beene ſure of protection from his little Grace, and have beene by him defended, and maintained our meanes and revenues, augmented not diminiſhed, and might have riſen to great preferment; but now all theſe our hopes are fruſtrate, our grand Patron of our infirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies is in Limbo, his little
<pb facs="tcp:156555:3"/>honour is now coverted to great diſgrace, which if he had had but the knowledge to predicted his fate, he would have endeavoured to have preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it. But he was it ſeemes ſo confident of his power and ſafety in his place of dignity, that if <hi>Auguſtus Ceſar</hi> had been now to warre againſt him, he could not be vanquiſhed. But wee may ſee how vaine a thing it is to truſt in riches, in fri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds, or in the favour of princes in the time of danger, for nothing is able to defend from the juſt vengeance of God, againſt hainous tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors and offendours: And if wee had but thought in the leaſt manner of theſe times, wee would have been more cautious in ſeeking the favour of great men, and ſubmitting our ſelves to their wills be they never ſo refractory from that which is good, for hopes of a little prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but truly I thought as I was taught that it was no ſinne to uſe Ceremonies, but that they were things of an indifferent quallity, and might be uſed without offence, but one comfort is I could not be brought to conceive the exerciſe of them to be of abſolute neceſſity to ſalvation, as ſome of the learned prelates would have it, but a thing that might be aſwell refuſed as uſed, yet I could never have the power to refuſe the uſe of them, for that preferment had the predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance in my braine, and I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onceived it better to live in ſome good faſhion, pleaſing to men, then in diſg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace and disfavour of the higher powers,
<pb facs="tcp:156555:3"/>daily in danger by them to be queſtioned and ſentenced to be pillored and loſe my eares, nay and per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hance fined and baniſhed, or perpetuall impriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nment, in goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-ſooth I loved my repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, eares, money and liberty better then ſo. But now the current of the ſtreame runnes in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother channell, I muſt goe with the tyde, leaſt now on the other ſide I may be in as much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger as I was before, for uſing theſe Ceremonies in the exerciſe of Religion is the beſt way to ſave my place, or to have ſome meanes allowed mee for the mrintenance of my ſelfe, wife, and children, for which purpoſe I might have in the time I have been preferred to this place, furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed my ſelfe with ſufficient monies which I have gotten by the by beſides my yearely penſion for ſinging; as for teaching to ſing young Artiſts in that Science, and other wayes, but that I was too much given to the Taverne and Ale-houſe, yea, and to play now and then at Venus Game with loving Citizens wives, whom I would almoſt perſwade I could procure pardon for that offence But thoſe joyes are gone, I muſt now betake my ſelfe to another courſe of life, or elſe I doubt I ſhall fare as thoſe doe in the Catehouſe: But what thinke you, will Organs and finging be put downe as well as Ceremonies.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:156555:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Organiſt.</hi> Truly I have heard there are many enemies towards us as to you, and ſtrive hard to bring us to deſtruction, ſo that our Ancient and famous Sound may be no more heard in this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Iſland of <hi>England,</hi> which hath beene glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for Zeale and Devotion in religion all over Europe: But yet we hold up and uſe our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion without contradiction, which I hope will ſtill be continued as a decent and comely thing in the Church, and a remembrance of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Law, and ſerves fitly to ſhew that we acknowledge in our religion aſwell the Law as the Goſpel, and agrees well to the retunying of both Teſtaments in print in this Kingdome, and that wee eſte me not one above the other, which is <hi>contrains;</hi> and I thinke Brother ſinger your profeſſion will hold ſtill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eriſt.</hi> If that continues I care not, for let them doe what they will with Ceremonies, I can aſ well ſing without a Surplice or black Hood and Tippet, or Cope, or any other Implement what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, if it ſhall be ſo thought fit and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for I am of the ſame religion with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and the State; If they command I will obey; and if there were no Parliament, then t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e greateſt in Authority in the State I would obey right or wrong, it's the beſt policie to ſerve the times, and change with the wind, for by that meanes I may be ſafe when others are queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, at home in peace and ſecurity when others
<pb facs="tcp:156555:4"/>for their Conſtancy are one time or another, be they in the true or falſe way, troubled and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, therefore my ſtudy and endeavour ſhall be to keep my ſelfe as much as I can, at all times, and upon all occaſions from danger.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Organs.</speaker>
               <p>Wel Brother we wil talke more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this buſineſſe at this time, but referre the ſame till wee heare more, and then wee will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with our beſt wits what courſe will be beſt for us to take.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erist.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Let us then ſo doe. Farewell.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:156555:5"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wee may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> abjure our ſinging,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For Ceremonies bringing</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Into the Church, and ringing</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For the downfall of the Org<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas poore Organs.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Quiriſter may hang himſelfe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For wanting his diviner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elfe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He's ta'en now for a Clergy Elfe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Being drown'd in Superſtition,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas fond ſuperſtition.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Wren <hi>is now defil'd in's neſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſigned with the marke o'th Beaſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And powder'd now for a Lent Feaſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which made him ſeeme a</hi> regulus.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas poore</hi> regulus.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let Ceremonies then deplore</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their Fortune greater then before,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Downe Idols, Croſſes, Ceremonies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alas poore Ceremonies.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
